lived Lyle's weird farm stories
until quarter till,
and we are going to get rolling
now with our lovely, wonderful panel.
I'm going to let you
all organize yourselves.
Unless you want me to tell you in order.
I will, I will happily tell you in order.
And I will let you introduce yourselves
so that you can make the most use
of your time.
We are being recorded, and we can
commence. Zach, your first on my list.
So unless anybody says different,
I will turn it over to you.
That is okay with me
and hopefully you can see my screen.
Let me just make sure I can see the chat.
So if you need to tell me about time
I will keep an eye on that.
So all right well hi everyone.
My name is Waylon.
I'm a professor in digital studies
at the University of Mary Washington
and a member of the Yellow board.
And I'm going to be
talking about a project
that is very much a work in progress
and a little different for me.
So I hope it's interesting.
This is inspired by by several things,
but thinking about using machine
learning for both creative
and critical purposes at the same time.
The title, The Allusion to Necromancy
is inspired by Cannabis
Workshop at Yellow 200 2020, in Toronto,
where we practice,
I think techno necromancy, I think, was
the term used there,
but this has a more particular context,
as you'll see shortly.
I am interested in this talk
and this this ongoing kind of back burner
research project that I've been doing
for a while in Oscar Wilde.
And I should say, I'm not an Oscar Wilde
scholar or 19th century scholar
or anything like this.
I kind of stumbled
into this particular topic.
I'll talk a bit about that.
But Oscar Wilde is a a writer
known for his witty prose, short,
aphoristic statements in particular
that are very quotable, very memorable.
Many of them.
He tends to work with
Camus and parallelism and irony
and other rhetorical figures that are
nicely packed into short statements.
And so it's a recognizable kind of style,
or it feels like it is.
And part of the research year
is asking to what extent can that
kind of style be replicated
or simulated through computational means?
It is very, very short chunks of text.
So my intuition was that
the short texts are going to be resistant
to some of the style of metric statistical
modeling approaches that need more data,
that need more statistics
in order to actually produce
something that matches something else.
And so I thought
it was an interesting case to study.
So I want to give you this
first part of a phrase.
This is the first part of an aphorism
composed by Oscar Wilde.
To be thoroughly evil, one must have.
And that's all he wrote.
So the question that I'm exploring is
what could come next
or what should come next?
And if you have read a lot of Oscar Wilde,
or feel like you're fluent
in his style of writing or style, thinking
you might have some ideas.
You might be thinking about what
sorts of things could come next.
And this particular phrase,
actually a group of Oscar
Wilde scholars have explored this phrase.
Sandra Sandra
Leonard discovered this phrase in a
on the back of an unpublished manuscript
and then put it to the
readers of intentions,
which is a journal of the Oscar
Wilde Society, and essentially asked,
what do you all think?
What could come next?
And collected
and published a few of the best examples.
The Times Literary Supplement
also picked this up
and published some of their favorites,
and I'll read them here.
So to be thoroughly evil,
one should have an incorruptible mind.
To be thoroughly evil,
one should have never sinned.
one should have the face of an angel,
the heart of the devil,
and the brain of an accountant.
I think all fairly amusing
and all pretty good examples of the type
of characteristic inversions
that Oscar Wilde does.
So I came across this
because Chris Voss is my colleague here
at Mary Washington, and I saw him,
he posted about this on on Facebook
and I thought, you know, text completion,
finishing sentences.
I know how to do that. I know about this.
This is something we've been doing
a long time in computational literature.
This is the illustration from
the travesty generator
for micros example from the 1980s.
Stylistically similar text
is something that
there's a long tradition of people
doing this for avant garde
literary reasons
and for ways of exploring creative texts.
And so I wanted to try
to bring those tools
and those types of explorations
to bear on this very specific
scholarly question about Oscar Wilde.
So I put together a few things here,
and I'm just I'm sharing this
to kind of avoid me getting into the weeds
with a lot of examples.
So I've a QR code
if you're watching it that way, and I
will just also type it here.
This is
a few kind of web
things
that you can use to explore
some of the generations that I
ran up, the type store that correct.
That looks no I didn't.
That's http.
Well you know how to you can see it.
It's I'll open it up here to
so I can show it to you.
These are different ways of packaging
together various runs of generating text.
The first one at the top left
is using Markov
chain
and the other three are using a exact.
The other three are using a custom,
a fine tuned large language model
based on a large language
model called comma version 0.1.
And these are ways to.
I was interested in creating ways
to understand how the different parameters
affect the output.
Different different choices
that different inference parameters
can create the output.
Because my intuition is that,
or my guess is that this is a part of how
we as readers perceive these texts
and evaluate their credibility.
So I'll just
this one is just like a way to top left is
going to be lower temperature and top P,
and then top right is going to be higher.
So it's going to get more chaotic
as you move down into the right.
But you can move through that
in a two dimensional space.
This one
you use a slider to adjust both of those.
And I,
I stuck on this one
because I thought it was pretty good.
And these are a little bit ephemeral.
Each time it runs, it picks from a small
subset that matched those parameters.
So this one
it came up with to be thoroughly evil,
one should have the intellect of the good
and the brutality of the beasts.
So another kind of inversion
and pretty good.
Some nice alliteration there going on.
Okay, so a couple other things I can get.
I don't want to get to the methodology
really, but it's using comma v1
and which is trained on common file
which is a data set of open
access and public domain texts.
And it's all published
and you can peruse it.
So it's a it gets around one of those,
the opacity question
or the unfathomable, unfathomable
data question
or critique of large language models.
It's one way of responding to that,
and it gets to an area of research
around explainability
and interpretability of large language
models, which I think this work
hopefully can contribute to.
Okay,
so I wanted to share another aphorism.
This one says being dead
is the most boring experience in life.
That is, if one accepts being married
or dining with a schoolmaster.
Another decent quote. Pretty funny.
The question mark
there is because this is allegedly
authored by Oscar Wilde in 1923.
You may remember he died in 1900.
So this was something that was composed
and published posthumously.
Hester Travis Smith was a medium psychic
who channeled Oscar Wilde
and used the Ouija board
to interact with him and get his thoughts
on modern life and spiritualism,
and James Joyce and a lot of other things,
and published this in a book.
And also she collaborated with Oscar
Wilde on a play called Is It a Forgery?
So these are works that are using this,
the medium of mediumship,
I guess, to try to do the same thing
that the large language model
that I trained is doing, or the other
language models might be trying to do,
to mimic a particular kind of style.
And it's pretty interesting.
I mean, I went through
and I excerpted phrases
that had an aphoristic style to them.
The art, after all the art of living
is to accomplish the impossible.
The possible is an everyday occurrence.
I don't know if it's because I know
that these are written in a certain way,
or come from a certain source,
but they feel a little bit flatter to me.
But that could just be my bias
because I know the context.
It'd be interesting
to compare and contrast.
So when
Travis Smith published this work,
it's you.
It was discussed in the
The Occult Review publication,
and it was interesting how
the the commentary around
it hinged on the question of style.
So this was a letter to the editor by C.W.
Sol, who argued, there
is, I believe, no limit
to the extent to which an author's style
can be assimilated.
In other words, like, sure, it sounds like
Oscar Wilde, but anybody could do that.
That's not hard.
That is certainly not going to be so hard
as to justify a vindication
of evidence of the afterlife,
but not everyone agreed.
Arthur
Conan Doyle wrote a response to C.W.
soul and said, no, actually,
this is so distinctly wilder,
and this is so clearly Oscar Wilde's voice
that this is actually good evidence
of the afterlife.
This is a kind of a shorter blurb.
He wrote longer discussion of it
and had correspondence with Travis Smith,
but he even went
as far as saying that this is showing
that there is an Oscar Wilde.
There's a brain behind this.
There is a mind behind this.
I don't know.
Arthur Conan Doyle, who you may have heard
of the other interest in spiritualism.
He was trying to learn more
about these things and wrote
quite a lot about, yeah,
yeah, spiritualism and the afterlife.
And this was interesting to me
because he's using style
as the main piece of evidence
to contribute to the
belief in the afterlife.
So as I'm thinking about this,
like I said, it's a work in progress
and I'm trying to understand
or think about possible next steps.
One of the things I want to try to do
is create enough text
with different models,
but create enough text to subject them
to a style of metric comparison
to see to what extent.
First of all, Wilde's
text is, as Arthur Doyle
asserts,
distinct enough from everything else
that it stands alone.
But then see where Trevor
Smith texts fits on that.
Maybe she got pretty close.
And then I'm curious
to see, to the extent,
the extent to which her automatic writing
might be more similar to an LM
generated text.
At the same time, you know, as I said,
this is kind of a sort of project.
It starts to feel that way.
But I have enjoyed the output, and
I've been enjoying reading it on its own.
Right.
As just a way to appreciate
Oscar Wilde's thought.
And sometimes the works that are output
are clever enough
sounding that it raises questions
about memorization.
And I've been.
I have an evaluation
checking to see if these are things
that are just ripping off quotes
from Oscar Wilde, and so far, not really.
Which is interesting because Trevor
Smith was accused of doing that.
When you look at some of these works,
this is a different quote of hers.
So the being dead is the most
that was the most boring thing in life.
That was her
the most boring experience in life.
That was her completion.
I turned my wilder Wilding aphorisms
trained model on her prompt,
or the first part of her sentence
as a prompt to kind of see if they to see
if they aligned or see
to what extent they might align.
And it couldn't get anything very similar.
It almost always went to the most
something in the world.
The world was almost
always the the end of that sentence,
but it came up with some pretty clever,
I think, turns of phrase.
The most delightful thing in the world.
The only people who are really
and absolutely alive are the dead.
It sounds like something
Oscar Wilde would say or write about.
I also like the there are a lot
that go to expense and cost
related to death,
so the most expensive thing in the world
is being dead
is the most expensive thing in the world.
It is the only thing for which one
has to pay the whole price at once.
Not really sure
what it means,
but sounds kind of profound.
So these are things where I think
they're interesting for me to try
to explore.
Explainability as a question around
large language models,
to see the extent to which parameterizing
and exposing the parameters
of the generation can help us understand
how it reaches certain outputs.
But ultimately, I'm finding it
enjoyable as a kind of
literary expression in its own right.
So that's it. Thank you.